All right, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is כ"ז Chaf
Zayin בבא בתרא Bava Batra 27. We are the last דף daf
of the פרק. perek. We are a little behind, we're picking up
on כ"ו עמוד ב' Chaf Vav Amud Bet 26B. We're going to
do a quick review of some of what we did yesterday. We're
starting six lines down, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. Okay, and והחופר
בור שיח ומערה קוצץ והעצים שלו. V'hayochfer bor shiach u-me'arah koteitz v'hayitzim
shelo. So the
משנה Mishnah says that if somebody plants a tree
near your boundary line, property line, and the and the roots go
into your underneath your ground, and then you are digging a pit
or well, when you hit the roots, you're allowed to cut the
roots to continue to dig your pit or well straight down and
the wood of the roots, who gets to keep the wood? It
says belong to him.
But the question of who is the him is not clear in
the משנה. Mishnah. So the גמרא Gemara says as follows: בעי מיניה
יעקב הדווא מרב חסדא. Ba'ei minei Yaakov Hadava me-Rav Chisda. So יעקב
הדווא Yaakov Hadava asked רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, עצים של מי, eitzim
shel mi, who does the wood of the roots belong to? Do
they belong to the owner of the tree or they belong to
the person whose yard they're in? אמר
ליה תניתוה. Amar lei tanitua. We taught it in a ברייתא, baraita,
excuse me, in a משנה. Mishnah. שורשי האילן של הדיוט הבאים בשל
הקדש, shorshei ha-ilan shel hedyot haba'im be-shel hekdesh, if you have a
tree planted in a yard that does not belong to the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, belongs to a layperson, and the roots go underground
and they go into a neighboring yard which belongs to the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, לא נהנין ולא מועלין. lo nehenin v'lo mo'alin. Those
you cannot, you're not rabbinically allowed to derive benefit from them because
they're in הקדש hekdesh property, but they don't genuinely belong to הקדש
hekdesh and therefore
there's no מעילה, me'ilah, there's no biblical מעילה. me'ilah. So אי אמרת
בתר אילן אזלינן, i amarta batar ilan azlinan, so this indicates that
the ownership, he says, the argument is, of the roots belongs to
the tree, not the yard they're in. Because, were we, because why?
If we, it makes sense if we go by the tree, משום
הכי לא מועלין. mishum hachi lo mo'alin. That's why because they come
from a tree that belongs to a layperson, there's no prohibition of
מעילה me'ilah even though they enter into the yard of הקדש. hekdesh.
So, and which would prove therefore that the roots that grow from
one yard to the next, they still belong to the owner of
the original tree. אלא אי אמרת בתר קרקע אזלינן, Ella i amarta
batar karka azlinan, but were you to go by the define the
ownership by the property that they're in, אמאי לא מועלין, amai lo
mo'alin, why would there not be מעילה? me'ilah? So for me, he
says, this is a clear proof that it ultimately they belong to
the owner of the tree and when you therefore cut into them,
you give them back to the owner of the tree. So the
response is, the גמרא Gemara is not happy with that. אלא מאי,
Ella mai, says the גמרא, Gemara, בתר אילן אזלינן, batar ilan azlinan,
you think that this makes sense to say you go by the
owner of the tree? אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, let's look at the
end of that משנה. Mishnah. של הקדש הבאים בשל הדיוט, shel hekdesh
haba'im be-shel hedyot, if you have the reverse, that the roots are
coming from a tree planted in the property of owned by the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and they go underground into the property of
a layperson,
אימא סיפא, eima seifa, where are we, של הקדש הבאים בשל הדיוט,
shel hekdesh haba'im be-shel hedyot, לא נהנין ולא מועלין, lo nehenin v'lo
mo'alin, same המלאכה, hamelakha, you're not rabbinically allowed to benefit from them,
but there is no prohibition of מעילה. me'ilah. So now that doesn't
make sense either. ואי בתר אילן אזלינן, ve-i batar ilan azlinan, were
you to go by the tree,
אמאי לא מועלין, amai lo mo'alin, why would there not be מעילה
me'ilah since they're coming from a הקדש hekdesh tree?
So you see this really doesn't make sense either way. You're not
totally going by the tree, you're not totally going by the yard
because in neither case is there מעילה. me'ilah. מידי איריא
בגידולין הבאים לאחר מיכן, Mi-di irya be-gidulin haba'im le-achar mikan, so the
גמרא Gemara says, really says the גמרא, Gemara, עסקינן, as'kinan, so you
know what really says the גמרא, Gemara, you're right. The reason here
there's no clear מעילה me'ilah is that we're dealing with stuff that
grow after you sanctify the tree itself. So after you sanctify the
tree, then the roots continue to grow, there's not going to be
מעילה me'ilah by those roots. So therefore in neither case, if it's
a if it's a tree that is sanctified, a הקדש hekdesh tree
and the roots grow and they grow underground, even if they didn't
grow into the land of the layperson, even if they were just
growing in land of הקדש, hekdesh, there would be no מעילה me'ilah
because they grew after the tree was sanctified. And certainly in the
case where they grew from a tree that is not הקדש, hekdesh,
just because they grew in הקדש hekdesh land would not be enough
to make it מעילה. me'ilah. Even though it might be owned by
הקדש, hekdesh, and this is really another point that the גמרא Gemara
is not getting into, right? Why is growth afterwards not הקדש? hekdesh?
I don't understand, it grew from a הקדש hekdesh tree, maybe it's
even growing in a field of הקדש, hekdesh, but the point is
it's not enough that it's owned by הקדש, hekdesh, it was not
something that was verbally sanctified and therefore there's not going to be.
any tree whether wherever the tree was and wherever it grew into
and that explains what's going on here in this משנה Mishnah and
it really does not prove our case as to who owns it
because it would be true even by a הקדש Hekdesh tree that
the roots continue to grow even in הקדש Hekdesh land. אלא בגידולין
באחרונה עסקינן Ela bigidulin ba'acharona askinan וכסבר ve'chasavar אין מעילה בגידולין ein
me'ilah bigidulin there is no מעילה me'ilah by the stuff that grew
afterwards regardless of who owns them so we really do not have
the answer to our question reconciled you cannot really prove it from
that משנה. Mishnah. רב פפא אמר לא קשיא כאן בתוך שש עשרה
אמה כאן בחוץ לשש עשרה אמה Rav Papa amar lo kashya kan
betoch shesh esreh amah kan bechutz leshesh esreh amah actually is a
difference with within sixteen אמות amot and outside of sixteen אמות amot
that what do you call that when
does it say that if it grew from הדיוט hedyot into הקדש
Hekdesh land it goes by the tree and there's no מעילה me'ilah
when it's within the first sixteen אמות amot but after the first
sixteen אמות amot it's no longer connected to the tree and therefore
the end of the ברייתא braita that says when the הקדש Hekdesh
grows into the הדיוט hedyot land there's no מעילה me'ilah therefore there's
no מעילה me'ilah after sixteen אמות amot but within the sixteen אמות
amot since it grew from הקדש Hekdesh tree there would be מעילה.
me'ilah. Now that's a very difficult read of the ברייתא braita we're
going to see sixteen אמות amot come up in a second that
we only consider the initial sixteen אמות amot of the spreading of
the roots to be sort of directly where the tree is getting
its sustenance from but anyway it's a very strange read to the
ברייתא braita because then the determinant factor a key part of the
determinant factor within sixteen אמה amah or outside of sixteen אמה amah
is not mentioned in the ברייתא braita but nevertheless according to this
answer he's basically arguing that it does belong to the owner of
the tree within sixteen אמות amot and actually if it was coming
from הקדש Hekdesh tree there would be מעילה me'ilah within sixteen אמות.
amot. Okay but anyway there is not really a proof that's just
one way of אוקימתא okimta of that משנה Mishnah there's really no
proof from the משנה Mishnah how to read our משנה Mishnah who
gets to own the roots is it the owner of the tree
or the owner of the field. Now we are going to look
at this issue of sixteen אמות amot with a very interesting teaching
of עולא. Ulla. אמר עולא Amar Ulla says עולא Ulla this is
now about ten lines from the bottom at the two dots. אילן
הסמוך למצר בתוך שש עשרה אמה גזלן הוא. Ilan hasamuch lemeitzer betoch
shesh esreh amah gazlan hu. If somebody goes ahead and puts a
tree within sixteen אמות amot of the boundary line between his property
and his neighbor's property he is a stealing from his neighbor's property
because the basic argument is that the roots will grow and they
will draw nutrients and sustenance within sixteen אמות amot so you are
essentially stealing from the nutrients of your friend's property up to sixteen
אמות amot because your roots are growing underneath from the base of
the tree. Now this would suggest that you're not allowed to do
it if you're calling somebody a גזלן gazlan of course the problem
is that our משנה Mishnah makes it clear that you are the
משנה Mishnah says the whole issue of distancing from the boundary line
from the border line is only in order to give enough room
for there to be a plow four אמות amot if there's a
wall you can plant right up to the boundary line maybe twenty-five
אמות amot if there's a well but otherwise you're allowed to plant
right up to the boundary line so תוספות Tosafot points out that
even though it's quite ironic even though it says גזלן הוא gazlan
hu it does not mean it's forbidden it is permissible at the
end of the day you're planting in your land and the roots
grow
afterwards and you're not directly stealing anything and this is just a
normal way of operating and therefore you're really not prohibited to plant
something nearby even though the roots will grow and it will make
some drawing on the nutrients however because you are to some degree
taking the nutrients גזלן gazlan in like quote marks therefore the real
relevance of עולא Ulla's is the next statement גזלן הוא gazlan hu
and the real relevance is not that it's prohibited to do this
but ואין מביא ממנו בכורים. ve'ein meivi mimenu bikurim. You don't bring
בכורים bikurim because when you bring בכורים bikurim if I'm planting my
tree next to sixteen אמה amah of your land and then I'm
going to bring בכורים bikurim from all the pomegranates let's say or
whatever and I'm going to say האדמה אשר נתתה לי ha'adamah asher
natata li I brought the first fruits of the land which you
have given to me these are not all the fruits of the
land that you God have given to me you're also part of
the fruits of the land that you've given to my neighbor because
they were growing from the nutrients from his land so the line
of גזלן gazlan is not to say it's prohibited but just to
acknowledge that some of the nutrients are coming from the other land
and therefore you would not bring בכורים. bikurim. All right so ואין
מביא ממנו בכורים ve'ein meivi mimenu bikurim now מנא ליה לעולא הא
Mina lei le'Ulla ha where did עולא Ulla get this sixteen אמות
amot even though we said it a minute ago where is it
coming from אילימא מדתנן Ilima mid'tenan we taught in the משנה Mishnah
עשר נטיעות המפוזרות בתוך בית סאה esser netiot hamefuzarot betoch beit se'ah
if you have fifteen saplings of trees that are planted in a
space of בית סאה. beit se'ah. בית סאה beit se'ah is an
area that you could plant a סאה se'ah of grain, and it
is basically twenty-five hundred square אמות. amot. The חצר chatzer of the
משכן, mishkan, the courtyard of the משכן, mishkan, and it is fifty
אמה ama by a hundred, which is five thousand square אמות, amot,
and that's called a בית סאתיים. beit satayim. So half of that,
a בית סאה, beit se'ah, is twenty-five hundred square אמות. amot. So
if you have tree saplings, ten saplings planted in that area, the
הלכה halacha is חורשין כל בית סאה בשבילן עד ראש השנה. chorshin
kol beit se'ah bishvilan ad rosh hashana.
And it's ערב שמיטה, erev shmita, so for a lot of things
ערב שמיטה erev shmita you have to stop, you have to do
like a, you know, תוספת tosefet and you're not allowed מוסיפין מחול
על הקודש mosifin mechol al hakodesh and you're not allowed to work
the land even before ראש השנה. rosh hashana. But the הלכה halacha
is you are allowed to work the land in the immediate area
of where there are trees as opposed to if it's like a
land where you grow grain, you're allowed to work that land right
up to ראש השנה, rosh hashana, and what is the distribution that
we say that entire space is sort of needed and connected to
the trees? It is when it is
ten saplings distributed in twenty-five hundred square אמות. amot. Okay, so that's
where we say that that whole land there is all all the
trees sort of need that entire land around them and you're allowed
to work the entire land right up to ראש השנה rosh hashana
of שמיטה. shmita.
It's a הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha lemoshe misinai. Now, כמה kama so
now that shows you that each of those trees needs a certain
amount of land or is drawing on the nutrients of a certain
amount of land. Let's do the math. כמה הוו להו? kama havu
lehu? So how many how much how much area is there in
a בית סאה? beit se'ah? תרי אלפין וחמש מאה גרמידי. trei alfin
vachamesh mea garmidi. Twenty-five hundred אמות. amot. גרמידי garmidi is an אמה.
ama. לכל חד וחד, lechol chad vechad, כמה מטי להו? kama matla
lehu? So divide that by ten, so twenty-five hundred אמות amot how
many אמות amot is required for each tree? כמה מטי ליה? kama
matla lei? מאתן וחמשין. matan vachamshin. Two hundred and fifty אמה ama
is needed per tree. הא לא הוי דעולא. ha lo havi de-Ulla.
That doesn't fit עולא. Ulla. Now why not? Because עולא Ulla said
sixteen אמות amot for you know is the tree draws on. Now
if you do that you'll think about the tree in a center
of a circle and you make a circle which has sixteen אמה
ama radius so that's going to be sixteen squared times pi. Okay,
we'll get to that in a minute because the גמרא Gemara has
not yet realized it's a circle. So it would be thinking that
שמואל Shmuel would be the tree in the center and it would
be a square. So sixteen אמה ama from each point of the
tree you know to each edge of the square is a square
that is thirty-two by thirty-two אמות, amot,
which is thirty-two squared is nine sixty and sixty-four is is one
thousand and twenty-four.
So one that would be one thousand and twenty-four אמות amot per
tree and here we only have two hundred and fifty אמות amot
per tree. So it's not at all comparable to עולא's Ulla math
about how much area around a tree does a tree draw on.
Even if you go from a square to a circle.
ואלא מדתנן, ve'ela miditnan, so the גמרא Gemara says fine, forget that
משנה. mishna. That משנה mishna was about saplings. Saplings need less. Let's
talk about the next משנה mishna that talks about trees themselves. ואלא
מדתנן. ve'ela miditnan. שלושה אילנות של שלושה בני אדם. sheloshah ilanot shel
sheloshah benei adam. Three trees belonging to three separate people and they're
all in a shared space. Can you work that land right up
to ערב שמיטה? erev shmita? How much is that space considered to
be needed to for the sustenance of the three trees? הרי אלו
מצטרפין וחורשין כל בית סאה בשבילן. harei elu mitztarfin vechorshin kol beit
se'ah bishvilan.
Also, even if they belong to separate people you can treat it
as one unit and you can plow the entire בית סאה beit
se'ah right up to ראש השנה. rosh hashana. So this is basically
saying while by saplings it's ten saplings, by trees it's three trees
the whole בית סאה. beit se'ah. So let's do the math. Continuing
top of כ"ז עמוד א'. chaf zayin amud alef. כמה הוו להו?
kama havu lehu? תרי אלפין וחמש מאה גרמידי. trei alfin vachamesh mea
garmidi. So how much did we say was a בית סאה? beit
se'ah? Twenty-five hundred אמות. amot. לכל חד וחד כמה מטי ליה? lechol
chad vechad kama matla lei?
So twenty-five hundred divided by three is how much? תמני מאה ותלתין
ותלת ותילתא. tmonei mea utlatzin utlat v'tilsa. Eight hundred and thirty-three, right,
eight hundred times three is twenty-four hundred, thirty-three and a third is
another hundred, twenty-five hundred. Eight hundred and thirty-three. אכתי נפישי לדעולא. akati
nefishei lide-Ulla.
So עולא Ulla is much larger, because עולא Ulla is thirty-two squared
which is what did we say that was? One thousand and twenty-four.
So עולא's Ulla amount of area needed for a tree is a
lot bigger, one thousand twenty-four than eight hundred and thirty-three. לא דק.
lo dak. All right, he wasn't being so precise. So the גמרא
Gemara says one minute. אימר דאמרינן לא דק, eimar de'amrinan lo dak,
when can you say somebody is not being precise? לחומרא. lechumra. If
they're rounding out and being more מחמיר. machmir. לקולא לא דק? lekula
lo dak? מי אמרינן mi amrinan we don't say that if it's
going to be מיקל meikel you're not precise. If שמואל Shmuel is
saying you're exempt from ביכורים Bikkurim anywhere within sixteen אמות ammos of
your neighbor's yard, and the reality is is that the amount that
a tree needs is not a thousand twenty-four square אמות, ammos, but
it's less, eight hundred thirty-three, then really your exemption from ביכורים Bikkurim
is only if you're going to be much closer to your neighbor's
yard, not sixteen אמות, ammos, maybe ten אמות ammos or whatever it'll
be, nine אמות, ammos, something, whatever the math is, okay? So you
cannot say that he was not being precise because he's getting you
off from the obligation of ביכורים, Bikkurim, so he's not going to
say a number that is bigger than the right number that would
exempt you. מי
אמרינן? mi amrinan? So the גמרא Gemara now finally gets to the
difference between a square and a circle.
מי סברת בריבוע קאמרינן? בעיגול קאמרינן. Mi savrat b'rivua kamrinan? B'igul kamrinan.
No, no, no, no, no. You were doing עולא, Ulla, you were
saying sixteen in each direction, you were making a square, thirty-two by
thirty-two. We're not talking about a square; we're talking about a circle,
right? If the tree needs sixteen אמות ammos in every direction, then
the tree is at the center and you have a radius of
sixteen going all the way around. Now, so what how so we
did the math a thousand twenty-four,
you know, that was for a square. How much is the area
of a circle inscribed within a square? Less than a square. So
the גמרא Gemara says,
מכדי כמה מרובע יתר על העיגול? רביע. Michdi kama meruba yater al
ha'igul? Revia. A quarter. Now, now that's not really true. Let's think
about this. Let's imagine a case where you had a radius of
one. So the circle would be pi r squared would be pi,
three point one four. The circle
the the square, if you had a center and you had one
in each direction from the center and you drew a square, that
would be each side would be two, so it'd be four. So
the ratio would be four to pi, four to three point one
four. But the גמרא Gemara understands that pi is three. So once
the גמרא Gemara works with a working understanding of pi as three,
then the ratio of a square to a circle is four to
three. So it is a quarter bigger than the circle inside. If
you take away a quarter of the area of the square, you
will get the area of the inscribed circle if we treat pi
as three. Alright, so what would that be? So you could sort
of say we just did the math, thirty-two squared gets you a
thousand twenty-four. You would do you take a quarter off of that,
so four divided by a thousand twenty-four is two and then twenty-four
is
well, whatever. Let's see.
Let me do this math here. So a thousand twenty-four divided by
four is two fifty-six. So a thousand twenty-four minus two fifty-six will
get you seven sixty-eight. So that's one way to figure out the
area of the circle. The other, you know, go from the square
and work back: seven sixty-eight. The other would be to do to
just do pi r squared. So you would have sixteen squared is
gets you two fifty-six and then times three gets you seven sixty-eight.
Okay, so either way, if we make pi as three, we're going
to get the circle now to be seven sixty-eight. So let's take
a look. מכדי כמה מרובע יתר על העיגול? רביע. פשו להו שבע
מאה ושיתין ותמני. Michdi kama meruba yater al ha'igul? Revia. Pashu lehu
sheva mea v'shittin v'tamni. So now you're left with seven sixty-eight. If
you go from one thousand twenty-four and you reduce a quarter, you
get seven sixty-eight, or you do sixteen squared times three, you get
seven sixty-eight. So now if עולא Ulla says that a tree gets
nutrients from sixteen אמות ammos in all directions, you need seven hundred
sixty-eight square אמות. ammos. Okay. The however the משנה Mishnah about the
three trees in a בית סאה Beit Seah had eight hundred thirty-three.
So actually that shows that a tree needs a little more than
sixteen אמות ammos of nutrients because it when it would get eight
hundred thirty-three אמות ammot of surrounding would it be drawing its nutrients
from, as opposed to just seventy-sixty as opposed to just what do
you call it, seven hundred sixty-eight. So let's see how what the
גמרא Gemara does with it. Now I should also say of course
that if you actually used the real pi for עולא Ulla and
you did sixteen squared, two fifty-six, and you did that times three
point one four,
so then what you would actually get is something very very close.
Then you would get right sixteen squared is excuse me is two
fifty-six, excuse me, times three point one four is eight hundred three
compared to the eight hundred thirty-three that we have in the משנה.
Mishnah. Now you're dealing with something extremely extremely close. But that's not
exactly how the גמרא Gemara resolves it. So let's take a look
at what the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay, אכתי פשו פלגא דאמתא, Achti pashu palga d'amta, okay,
says the גמרא, Gemara, but it's no longer sixteen; it's more like
it's sixteen and a half in each direction. And that's what you
need to get you 833, which is what we see from the
משנה. Mishnah. So the גמרא Gemara says: היינו דלא דקו לחומרא לא
דקו. hainu delo daku lechumra lo daku. Fine, that's what we meant
that he wasn't being precise, but he was being מחמיר, machmir, he
was saying, you know, within 16 אמות, amos, you are exempt from
ביכורים. bikurim. That is true. The actual reality is within 16 and
a half אמות amos of your neighbor's yard, you're exempt from ביכורים.
bikurim. He was rounding off, but it wasn't leading to a קולא.
kula. You know, out of 16 אמות, amos, you know, sometimes you'll
be exempt, sometimes you'll be חייב, chayav, but within 16 אמות amos
you are always exempt. Now our
גרסא girsa says 16 and a half. If you do the 16
and a half math,
16.5 times 16.5, and then you multiply that by 3, you get
816. That's getting closer. However, רש"י Rashi points out and תוספות Tosafot
points out that the better גרסא girsa is 16 and two-thirds. And
if you do 16.66 times 16.66,
you'll get 278 about, and you multiply that by 3, you get
833. It's pretty much exactly the same. Okay, and the long תוספות
Tosafot here is just to figure out how to do that type
of a math. All right, anyway, that's שמואל's Shmuel's idea that a
tree needs about 16 or 16 and a half אמות amos in
each or 16 and two-thirds in each direction, and therefore if it's
right up against the neighbor's yard and it's drawing from the nutrients,
you can't say אדמה שנתת לי. adamah shenasata li. So if it's
within those 16 אמות, amos, and therefore you are exempt from ביכורים.
bikurim. All right, תא שמע, ta shema, so now the גמרא's Gemara's
going to see if we really, if this argument really holds. Come
in here.
הקונה אילן וקרקעו, hakoneh ilan vekarkao, מביא וקורא. mevi vekoreh. It says
if you buy a tree and the land directly with it, you
bring ביכורים bikurim because you can say אדמה שנתת לי. adamah shenasata
li. מאי לאו כל שהוא, mai lav kol shehu, doesn't that imply
even a small amount of land, like the land directly underneath it,
you don't need all the land surrounding it? So the גמרא Gemara
says, לא, ט"ז אמות, lo, tes zayin amos, no, we'll say it
means the land that goes with it meaning 16 אמות amos in
each direction, which is obviously a huge difference and you would have
expected the משנה Mishnah to say it. So the evidence clearly is
against עולא. Ulla. תא שמע, ta shema, come in here. קונה שני
אילנות בתוך של חבירו, koneh shenei ilanos besoch shel chaveiro, מביא ואינו
קורא. mevi ve'eino koreh. If you buy two trees then in your
friend's yard, then the assumption is that when you buy two trees,
you're just buying the tree. Only if you buy three trees do
you automatically get the land that goes with, you know, that's near,
that the trees are on or that are between the three trees.
So the גמרא Gemara says if two you don't bring, הא שלשה
מביא וקורא, ha shelosha mevi vekoreh, the suggestion being, I mean actually
the משנה Mishnah continues and says it, as soon as you buy
three trees you do bring ביכורים bikurim even though presumably in that
case all you get is the immediate land that's between the trees.
מאי לאו כל שהוא, mai lav kol shehu, doesn't it mean even
the smallest amount of land? לא, הכא נמי ט"ז אמות, lo, hacha
nami tes zayin amos, no, we'll say that what it means is
that when you buy three trees, you don't just get the immediate
land underneath it or underneath the foliage, you know, but you actually
get everything within a 16 אמה amah radius. Now תוספות Tosafot points
out that actually the משנה Mishnah in other places makes it clear
that you what you get is directly underneath it and under the
foliage. So תוספות Tosafot says well what that would mean is that
if the foliage, you know, the awning extends beyond 16 אמות, amos,
you get everything up to that. But even if it doesn't go
that far, the argument here, again not at all פשט, pshat, the
argument here is that you would always get at least 16 אמות
amos in each side. תא שמע, ta shema, come in here. רבי
עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, קרקע כל שהוא, karka kol shehu, even
if you have the smallest amount of land, חייב בפאה, chayav bepe'ah,
you would bring פאה pe'ah if you grew a few stalks of
wheat, you know, you'd have to leave one stalk as פאה pe'ah
no matter how big or small the land, ובביכורים uvevikurim and if
you had some tree growing on it you would bring
ביכורים, bikurim, וכותבין עליו פרוזבול vechosvin alav prosbol and when you're writing
a פרוזבול prosbol so the שמיטה shemitah does not annul the debt,
right, and you hand over your debts to בית דין, beis din,
you only do that if the person who owes you the money
has land because a standard loan is a loan that you write
only you give only a loan to somebody if they have land
so that you have liens and you can collect, and only by
standard loans did חז"ל chazal make the תקנה takanah of פרוזבול prosbol
that would allow you to hand it over to בית דין beis
din to collect after שמיטה. shemitah. Another way of understanding that is
if there is land, then it is not like the loan is
totally uncollectible since the land is immediately available for being seized, you
know, and there are liens on the land. The prohibition by שמיטה
shemitah is לא יגוש את רעהו ואת אחיו, lo yigosh es re'ehu
ve'es achiv, do not like, you know, do not
like make demands of the loan, and this is as, and this
is already property that is to some degree under your control, so
it's not like you're exacting the loan from your friend once there
is land with liens. Okay, so even a tiny amount of land
would suffice for that. Top of כ"ז עמוד ב, kaf zayin amud
bais, ונקנין עמו נכסים שאין להם אחריות, veniknin imo nechasim she'ein lahem
achrayos, and also the principle that when and also the principle that
when you sell land you can transfer chattel, even chattel not on
the land. So if I tell you a square inch of of
of real estate and you buy real estate through כסף שטר או
חזקה, kesef shtar o chazakah, so you do it by giving me
a dollar, or we do it by writing a שטר, shtar, I
can say by transferring to you this square inch of real estate
I'm also transferring to you, you know, I don't know, my warehouse
filled with furniture, everything in the warehouse. So that's the principle that
when you transfer property real estate you can transfer chattel with it.
All of that can even be on the smallest amount of land.
What's relevant for us is that it says that ביכורים bikurim even
on the smallest amount of land, which goes against עולא's Ula's argument,
all of this goes against עולא's Ula's position. So the גמרא Gemara
says הכא במאי עסקינן hacha bimai askinan again top of כ"ז עמוד
ב', Chaf Zain Amud Bet, what are we talking about? בחיטי be'chitei
that you're talking about not ביכורים bikurim isn't only pomegranates, right, it's
all of the שבעת המינים, Shivat HaMinim, so it also includes ארץ
חטה ושעורה. eretz chitah u'seorah.
So even if you have one stalk of wheat growing on a
square inch of land, that's what we're talking about, we're not talking
about trees, which for trees it would only be if it were
sixteen אמות. amos. בחיטי דייקא
נמי דקתני כל שהוא. be'chitei dayka nami d'katani kol shehu. The גמרא
Gemara says you know what, that's actually a good point because it
says כל שהוא, kol shehu, even the tiniest amount. And if we're
talking about a tree you cannot have a tree in a square
millimeter, it would only so clearly we're talking about a scenario where
we'd be talking about something like wheat. Okay, שמע מינה. sh'ma mina.
Good point, at least that that's the case of that of that
of that משנה. mishnah. תא שמע ta sh'ma come and hear, we're
still not done trying to prove or disprove עולא. Ula. Come and
hear, תא שמע, ta sh'ma, אילן מקצתו בארץ ומקצתו בחוצה לארץ. ilan
miktzaso ba'aretz u'miktzaso b'chutz la'aretz. Let's say you have a tree that
is the boundary between ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and חוץ לארץ chutz
la'aretz goes right through the middle of the tree. All right, and
you've got whatever growing from it, figs, you know dates, pomegranates. So
and then you're plucking it all off of the tree. How do
you figure out what is what is טבל tevel and what is
not טבל? tevel? So it says the following, it says טבל וחולין
מעורבין זה בזה דברי רבי. tevel v'chulin me'uravin zeh bazeh divrei Rebbe.
רבי Rebbe says that yeah, you know, that the tree is it's
one unit of a tree, it's growing both from ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael and חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, you don't view it as like
two half trees stuck together and therefore any fruit that you pick
off of it is half טבל tevel and half חולין. chulin. So
if you had ten pounds of you know of whatever or you
know a ten ten gallons of of of dates, you'd separate off
one gallon you know of for מעשר—no, ma'aser a half a gallon
of מעשר ma'aser as opposed to one gallon for מעשר, ma'aser, whatever
it would be. Okay, so you would treat it as you know
you couldn't identify which is which, it's all a mix of טבל
tevel and חולין, chulin, but the amount of תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'ma'asros
you would take would be half of what it would be for
that normal amount. That's what רבי Rebbe says. ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר הגדל בחיוב חייב והגדל בפטור פטור. v'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer
hagadel bechiyuv chayav v'hagadel bep'tur patur. No,
you actually look every part of every fruit that is on you
know you look a boundary line going from the ground up into
the sky and every fruit that's on the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
side of the boundary line is understood to have grown in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael and every fruit that's on the חוץ לארץ chutz
la'aretz side is understood to have grown in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz
and the stuff on one side is טבל tevel and the stuff
on the other side is is not.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, עד כאן לא פליגי
אלא דמר סבר יש ברירה ומר סבר אין ברירה. ad kan lo
pligi ela demar savar yesh breira umar savar ein breira. Until now
the whole debate that we've understood there to be is whether you
say יש ברירה yesh breira or אין ברירה. ein breira. Now יש
ברירה yesh breira אין ברירה ein breira basically means is it's not
exactly the most obvious application of the ברירה breira case. The ברירה
breira case normally is you know something that happens later we retroactively
say that was always the way it was going to be. So
you know if like a good case that would be somewhat analogous
would be let's say it was grain that a yard that was
equally owned by a Jew and a non-Jew. And then after they
divided the grain, right, would then we could sort of say oh
the grain that in the end you decided the Jew decided to
take for his fifty percent ownership, that was the grain we will
sort of say was the you know grew from the Jew's owner
from from the part of the land that belonged to the Jew.
You know that was always the Jew's grain. And the part of
the grain that we gave to the non-Jew, even though the division
only happened after it grew and was harvested the whole thing, we'll
say that was always the non-Jew's. And if the Jew's was always
the Jew's, then it grew then this was grain that grew under
the ownership of a Jew and therefore it's חייב chayav in תרומות
ומעשרות trumos u'ma'asros because from the very beginning when it was growing
now retroactively that the Jew got this grain we say that this
was always the Jew's grain that had been growing in the land
to begin with. Here you don't have anything like that, it's not
like at the end you're awarding half of the stuff to ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael and half to חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz and you're
saying retroactively the stuff that we now you know you know put
in the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael box retroactively was always ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. So it's not exactly an obvious type of a case
of ברירה. breira. Based on something that happens now we retroactively say
it was always that to begin with. But the the point that
the גמרא Gemara is getting at is that even though the tree
is sort of one unit, the debate is, do we sort of
say that the stuff that's growing on the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
side is you know that's that's in the branches and on the
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael side is growing from the ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael half of the tree? And the stuff growing on the חוץ
לארץ Chutz La'aretz side is growing you know we'll have determined that
that was growing from the חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz part of the
tree. That's the debate, if you can actually split it that way
or not. Okay, that's a debate of רבי Rebbi and רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. אבל גד בפטור דברי הכל פטור,
Aval gad b'patur divrei hakol patur, but everybody agrees that the part
growing on the חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz side is exempt. And according
to עולא, Ulla, even the part growing on the חוץ לארץ Chutz
La'aretz side, if it is drawing off of the nutrients of ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, logically that should be חייב. chayav. Now, that is
not so clear that that is true according to עולא. Ulla. I
mean, עולא's Ulla's point that you're getting the nutrients and you can't
say אדמה שנתת לי adamah shenatata li could just be you know
a specific ביכורים Bikkurim הלכה halacha that you can't say this is
all my land if it if it grew off nutrients of somebody
else's land. That doesn't mean that the הלכה halacha of whether a
tree is whether the produce is חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות Terumot
u'Ma'asrot is defined by which nutrients it grew from as opposed to
you know whether it actually was planted on the ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael side or the חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz side. So it's not
exactly clear the way the גמרא Gemara is a applying ברירה breira
and b applying עולא. Ulla. But anyway that's the question. So according
to עולא Ulla shouldn't you always be obligated because it's always drawing
on ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael nutrients? So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אבל גד בפטור דברי הכל פטור הכא במאי עסקינן דמפסיק צונמא.
Aval gad b'patur divrei hakol patur, hacha b'mai askinan d'mafsik tzunma. We're
talking about a case, we had this before in the גמרא Gemara
in other cases, that there's like a a rock and a boulder
that's dividing going down the land you know right along the boundary
line. So anything that are the roots of one side they can't
be the roots don't you know of one side of the boundary
don't go into the other side across the boundary line and maybe
they also you know and they can't draw those nutrients on the
other side. So we're talking about a very special case here where
it is not drawing from the nutrients on the other side. All
right, so that's why yes the part that grew in the half
of פטור patur is פטור patur and the half that's חייב chayav
is חייב. chayav. So then what's the issue here? So ובמאי קמיפלגי,
U'vemai kamiflagi, what's the debate? אי הכי מאי טעמא דרבי דהדרי ערבי?
Ei hachi mai ta'ama d'Rebbi d'hadri arvi?
So what's the reason of רבי Rebbi that says therefore if there
is this rock that divides them underneath the ground, how come you
how can you say it's טבל tevel and חולין chullin mixed up,
isn't it literally half and half? So the גמרא Gemara says no
because they get because even though the the nutrients and the roots
are on each side then they feed into the trunk and those
feed the entire tree. And that's why רבי Rebbi says that in
the end wherever they're getting the nutrients the fruit that grows everything
is mixed all together. ובמאי קמיפלגי, U'vemai kamiflagi,
so what is the debate about? מר סבר אוירא מבלבל ומר סבר
האי לחודיה קאי והאי לחודיה קאי. Mar savar avira mevalbel u'mar savar
hai l'chudei ka'ei v'hai l'chudei ka'ei. That's what they debate. One says
that the stuff that grew from the nutrients of one side those
nutrients stay on the side that it that the roots were in
and therefore only the fruit only feed the fruit on that side
of the tree and the and the nutrients that came from the
roots on the other side only feed that side of the tree
and that's how come you can split the tree down the middle.
That's רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. And רבי Rebbi
says no wherever they're getting their nutrients in the end it's mixing
up into the tree and it's feeding all of the fruit. Okay.
So anyway that was interesting that the גמרא Gemara wanted a obviously
it was a very weak אוקימתא, okimta, a lot of weak אוקימתות
okimtot according to עולא, Ulla, besides which a little bit not direct
not a most obvious application of the principle of ברירה breira plus
also interesting the comparison of this question of whether you're חייב chayav
in תרומות ומעשרות Terumot u'Ma'asrot to this issue of עולא Ulla of
where is it getting its nutrients. Okay. Okay, ושש עשרה אמה וסלע,
V'shesh esrei ammah v'sela,
now the גמרא Gemara is going to say all right fine. So
that was all of our argument that questioning שמואל's Shmuel's argument that
it draws nutrients up to 16 אמות ammot or maybe whether it
does or doesn't draw nutrients up to 16 אמות ammot that that
should really matter for any area of הלכה, halacha, ביכורים, Bikkurim, תרומות
ומעשרות, Terumot u'Ma'asrot, whatever the case might be. But now the גמרא
Gemara is saying is really, if you're going to worry about where
it's drawing the nutrients from you're only going to worry up to
אמות? ammot? והתנן, V'hatnan, didn't we teach in our משנה: Mishnah: מרחיקין
את האילן מן הבור עשרים וחמש אמה, merchikin et ha'ilan min habor
esrim v'chamesh ammah, that you keep the tree 25 אמות ammot away
from the well? So it shows that you're concerned that the roots
will go up to 25 אמות. ammot.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye says מיהזל טפי אזלי. mehizal
tuvei azlei. No, no, no, the roots will go very far, who
knows they'll go 25 אמות, ammot, they'll go even further. אחלושי לא
מחלשי אלא עד שש עשרה אמה טפי לא מחלשי. Achlushi lo machalshi
ela ad shesh esrei ammah tuvei lo machalshi. They only weaken the
ground. It's funny he says weaken, the real point
that... The primary drawing of the nutrients are up to 16 אמות,
amot, not more than 16 אמות, amot, and that's why that's what
matters for the idea of בכורים. bikurim. It's funny he emphasizes not
drawing the nutrients, but whether it is weakening, you know, the soil,
I mean it'll invade the pit wherever it is, but in terms
of whether it's weakening the soil, only up to 16 אמות. amot.
Maybe he's going off of עולא's Ula's language of גזלן, gazlan, so
he's emphasizing the weakening idea, although the real point about עולא Ula
was where is it drawing the nutrients from? Okay, כי אתא רב
דימי אמר, Ki ata Rav Dimi amar, so when רב דימי Rav
Dimi came, he said, בעי מיניה ריש לקיש מרבי יוחנן, Ba'ei minei
Reish Lakish me-Rabbi Yochanan, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish asked רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, אילן הסמוך למצר בתוך שש עשרה אמה מהו? Ilan hasamuch lemetzar
betoch sheish-esrei ama mahu? What's the case if a tree is within
16 אמה ama of somebody's boundary line? אמר ליה, Amar lei, גזלן
הוא ואין מביאין ממנו בכורים, Gazlan hu ve'ein mevi'in mimenu bikurim, it's
a גזלן, gazlan, you're stealing nutrients. Again, fascinating even though it's not
forbidden to do it, but you would not bring בכורים bikurim as
a result. כי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן, Ki ata Ravin amar
Rabbi Yochanan, אחד אילן הסמוך למצר ואחד אילן הנוטה מביא וקורא. Echad
ilan hasamuch lemetzar ve'echad ilan hanoteh mevi vekorei. Now we finally have
a ruling against this, which all the evidence was against this. Whether
your tree is right up against somebody's boundary line, borderline, whether it
is the canopy is hanging over, nevertheless we are not that does
not have any impact for בכורים, bikurim, even if it is drawing
nutrients from your friend's land. על מנת כן הנחיל יהושע לישראל את
הארץ. Al menat kein hinchil Yehoshua le-Yisrael et ha'aretz. With that understanding,
יהושע Yehoshua bequeathed the land to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, that that
is not something that anybody has a right to be to complain
about. You know, it would make living impossible if you would not
be able to do that type of a thing, or if it
would be seen as inappropriate. Now again, the funny thing here is
that all along we were not saying it was forbidden, but the
idea of על מנת כן al menat kein means somehow that you
have rights to that. It's not considered that you're taking from somebody
else's land. Ultimately, you know, it's considered that you have those rights,
and since you have those rights, you can still say אדמה אשר
נתתה לי. Adamah asher natata li. All right, very strange sort of
ruling of עולא Ula about בכורים bikurim and about also the idea
that you could be calling somebody a גזלן gazlan and it still
not be a halachic problem, and how addressing the idea of על
מנת כן al menat kein by saying you're not a גזלן, gazlan,
you know, at the end of the day it's still not all
from your land. It is from your neighbor's land, but somehow because
you have the right to do it, that removes any problems of
אדמה אשר נתתה לי. Adamah asher natata li. Let's take a look
at the next משנה. mishnah. Getting near the end here. אילן שהוא
נוטה לשדה חבירו קוצץ מלא המרדע על גבי המחרישה. Ilan shehu noteh
lesadeh chaveiro kotzetz melo hamardea al gabei hamachreishah. So this is again
the idea that you need to be able to have you know
room in order to plow. So if you have a tree that
is right up against your friend's field where they're growing wheat and
it's the canopy is overhanging, so you can cut away at the
canopy to the height of the מרדע, mardea, which is like the
prod. You know, the person would be walking behind the animals and
with a stick and he would be raising the stick over them
and prodding the cow to do the plotting to do the plowing,
excuse me. So you can cut that type of height towards the
height of the person and the height at which he would hold
the stick by the width of the plow in order so that
the person in this yard can go ahead and plow the thing
even though there's an overhanging tree. ובחרוב ובשקמה, U-vecharuv u-veshikmah, and if
you're dealing with these other types of trees that are not not
fruit trees, a carob and a sycamore tree, so in
those types of cases, where are we? ובחרוב ובשקמה כנגד המשקולת, U-vecharuv
u-veshikmah keneged hamishkolet, because that would be opposite the plumb line. So,
you know, like you would a meaning you go straight down, so
anything that would be directly overhanging the the field,
your neighbor's field, you would make like a plumb line at the
at the border line and you could cut the entire overhang. You
know, and that is because these trees here, the carob tree and
the sycamore tree, just have such heavy foliage that it will the
shade will be very damaging to your property, so you are allowed
to cut the entire overhang against the plumb line, you know, the
the dividing line of the of the border line.
Okay, בית השלחין, Beit hashalchin, now if you have an irrigated field,
כל האילן כנגד המשקולת, Kol ha'ilan keneged hamishkolet, then there too because
any the shade would be not good for an irrigated field, you
can cut any part of the tree that overhangs opposite the plumb
line, meaning you do a straight border line, you go straight up
and you can cut any of the overhang, not only a carob
and a sycamore, but anything if it's a irrigated field because it
needs the
because the shade is damaging. אבא שאול אומר כל אילן סרק כנגד
המשקולת. Abba Shaul omer kol ilan srak keneged hamishkolet.
Only a what do you call it?
All non-fruit trees you cut opposite the plumb line. Plumb line. So
the גמרא Gemara is going to discuss immediately whether he is arguing
on the first case of the משנה Mishnah or the second case.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. איבעיא להו, Iba'i Lehu,
they raised the question: אבא שאול ארישא קאי או אסיפא קאי? Abba
Shaul Areisha Ka'i O Asayfa Ka'i? Is Abba Shaul going on the
first case or the second case? The first case said that when
it's coming to the need for plowing and it wasn't dealing not
dealing with an irrigated field, it made a distinction between between all
trees, you know, you could only cut to allow the plow guy
to get through, but with the carob and the sycamore you could
cut it all off. So is Abba Shaul saying on that not
just the carob and the sycamore, any non-fruit tree you can cut
everything away? That's one way of reading him, he's going on the
רישא, Reisha, he's being lenient or lenient to the guy who's field
it is, you can cut it all away if it's a non
if it's a non-fruit tree in the case of a non-irrigated field,
or is he responding to the סיפא, Sayfa, the irrigated field? That
the סיפא Sayfa said if it's the irrigated field you can cut
everything away and Abba Shaul is saying no, not everything, just non-fruit
trees. Is he being מקל Meikel or מחמיר? Machmir? First case or
second case? So תא שמע, Ta Shma, come and hear, דתניא, Detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא, Braita, בית השלחין, Beit Hashalchin, if it's
an irrigated field, אבא שאול אומר, Abba Shaul Omer, כל האילן כנגד
המשקולת, Kol Ha'ilan Kenegad Hamishkolet, you cut away all the tree opposite
the plumb line, מפני שהצל רע לבית השלחין, Mipnei Shehatzel Ra Leveit
Hashalchin, because the shade is bad for the irrigated field. So Abba
Shaul is explicitly allowing every tree to be cut away by the
irrigated field, which was the סיפא Sayfa of the משנה. Mishnah. So
שמע מינה, Shma Mina, ארישא קאי, Areisha Ka'i, so you see that
when Abba Shaul is saying the difference between fruit trees and not
fruit trees, he's not going on the irrigated field, the irrigated field
he is the author of the last line of the משנה. Mishnah.
The irrigated field he allows you to cut away any tree that's
overhanging, you know, any part of the overhang. So when he is
making a distinction between fruit trees and non-fruit trees, he's not going
on the second part, he's going on the רישא, Reisha, the first
part, when it's not an irrigated field, that the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma only allows you to totally cut away a sycamore and a
carob, and he allows you to cut away any non-fruit tree. שמע
מינה, Shma Mina, ארישא קאי, Areisha Ka'i, שמע מינה, Shma Mina, that
is a good point. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, מתניתין נמי
דייקא, Matnitin Nami Dayka, you can also get see this from a
close read of the text of the משנה, Mishnah,
דקתני, Dekatani, our משנה Mishnah says, כל אילן סרק, Kol Ilan Srak,
any non-fruit tree. אי אמרת בשלמא, Ei Amrat Bishlama, ארישא קאי, Areisha
Ka'i, if it's going on the first case of the משנה, Mishnah,
היינו דקתני, Hainu Dekatani, כל אילן, Kol Ilan, then the any is
more expansive and you understand it. You, תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, say
that only a carob and a sycamore you can cut it all,
all the overhang away, otherwise it's just to allow the plow, you
know, the plowing guy to get through. I, Abba Shaul, am going
to say not just the carob and the sycamore, any non-fruit-bearing tree.
I'm going to be more expansive. That works. אלא אי אמרת, Ela
Ei Amrat, אסיפא Asayfa קאי, Ka'i, but if it's on the end
case,
אילן סרק מבעי ליה, Ilan Srak Miba'i Lei, then in the second
case, the second case the משנה Mishnah said, if it's an irrigated
field you can cut away any tree, and if Abba Shaul is
coming and saying no, not any tree, just non-fruit-bearing trees, he shouldn't
have used the word כל, Kol, he should have said only אילן
סרק Ilan Srak you can cut away. So the word כל Kol
shows he's being more expansive, not more limiting. אלא לאו, Ela Lav,
שמע מינה, Shma Mina, ארישא קאי, Areisha Ka'i, שמע מינה, Shma Mina,
you see he's going on the first case. That is good evidence.
He's being more expansive that when it is overhanging and it is
a non-fruit-bearing tree, he will allow you to cut away the entire
overhang even in a case that it is not one of an
irrigated field. Okay, last משנה Mishnah of the second פרק. Perek. אילן
שהוא נוטה לרשות הרבים, Ilan Shehu Noteh Lerashut Harabim, קוצץ כדי שיהא
גמל עובר ורוכבו. Kotzetz Kedei Sheyehei Gamal Over Verokhvo. So if you
have a tree that is overhanging into the רשות הרבים, Rashut Harabim,
you know, it's like, you know, you have these overpasses on the
highways it tells you what the clearance is. So you got this
overhanging tree, you don't want somebody riding on a camel to get
knocked off by the branches of the tree. So you will cut
away the branches to the height that somebody can walk on that
path in רשות הרבים Rashut Harabim and on top of a camel
and not be impeded by the tree. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda
Omer, גמל טעון פשתן או חבילי זמורות. Gamal Ta'un Pishtan O Havilei
Zmorot.
Not a person a rider on a camel, you would measure it
by you would measure it by the height of a camel, which
is obviously very high, which is why we're talking about a camel,
a camel carrying flax or you know or or twigs. רבי שמעון
אומר, Rabbi Shimon Omer, כל האילן כנגד המשקולת מפני הטומאה. Kol Ha'ilan
Kenegad Hamishkolet Mipnei Hatuma.
No, not just to the height of the what do you call
it of the camel and whatever's on the camel, but you would
cut away the entire overhang no matter how high you go, similar
to the discussion before, you cut away the entire overhang because of
טומאה. Tuma. You don't want there to be maybe there would be
some part of a of a corpse underneath the tree, and you
know, this is how come כהנים kohanim have to be very careful
by cemeteries because of all the trees, and then the טומאה tumah
would be carried by the overhang. Anything under the overhang, that that
overhang would be on top of any person and some and a
corpse would make them טמא. tamei. So therefore you do not want
כהנים kohanim not to be able to go in רשות הרבים, reshut
harabbim, so you have to cut away any overhang, even if high,
even higher than the height of the camel and the rider because
to prevent people from becoming טמא. tamei. Let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. מן תנא דבניזיקין בתר אומדנא דהשתא אזלינן. Man tanna
de-binizikin batar umdana de-hashta azlinan.
So the גמרא Gemara says, it's all very nice, you want to
cut it away so that the person on the camel can pass
under it, but in the end branches are going to grow, and
they're going to keep on growing, and eventually what you cut away
now isn't going to last that long, isn't going to last forever.
So who says that when you're trying to remove things that are
hazards, it's enough to focus on the current situation and not on
what's going to happen later, later on? Because if you had to
worry about what's going to happen later on, you would have to
cut away more, maybe cut down the whole tree or who knows
what you would have to do. But how who allows you to
focus just on the here and now? בתר אומדנא דהשתא, batar umdana
de-hashta,
we go by assessing the current situation. אמר ריש לקיש מחלוקת שנויה
רבי אליעזר היא. Amar Resh Lakish machloket shnuyah Rabbi Eliezer hi. It's
a debate, you're right, and this is the position of רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. דתנן, de-tnan, we taught in a משנה mishna in בבא
קמא, Bava Kamma, אין חופרין חלל תחת רשות הרבים בורות שיחין ומערות,
Ein hofrin chalal tachat reshut harabbim borot sichin u-mearot, you cannot make
a cavity under the רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, you cannot dig, you
know, caverns or wells or subway tunnels or whatever you want to
dig because somebody might be walking over it and then it will
the roof will collapse and they'll collapse in, you know, it'll be,
it's not now a בור bor ברשות הרבים be-reshut harabbim because now
it's a tunnel underneath, but it might become one and it might
collapse. So you're not allowed to do it. רבי אליעזר מתיר בכדי
שתהא עגלה מהלכת וטעונה אבנים. Rabbi Eliezer matir bichde she-tehe agalah mehelechet
u-teunah avanim.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer permits it as long as it's a strong
enough roof that could that could, you know, withstand a
wagon filled with stones. So it seems like that's the debate, right?
Because why do the חכמים chachamim not allow it even in that
case? Because they feel that even if now it can withstand a
wagon filled with stones, eventually it'll get weaker and weaker and weaker
and it might eventually collapse. So it seems that our משנה mishna
that doesn't say you have to cut down the whole tree and
isn't concerned about the future is following a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
position. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. רבי יוחנן אמר
אפילו תימא רבנן. Rabbi Yochanan amar afillu tema rabbanan. No, it could
here we could work even like the רבנן. rabbanan. התם זימנין דמיפחת
ולאו אדעתיה. Hasam zimnin de-mifchat ve-lav adatei.
In the case of the tunnel underneath
רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, the ceiling can get weaker and nobody would
know, it'll slowly erode and then all of a sudden it'll collapse
and there'll be no advance warning. So that's why the רבנן rabbanan
don't want you to do it. אבל הכא קמא קמא קקייץ ליה.
Aval hacha kamma kamma ka-kayitz lei. Here, every little bit you can
regularly maintain it and you can regularly cut away if you see
that the branches are growing and it is no longer gives you
sufficient clearance. Now, you could of course, the point is, you know,
people are not regularly going and measuring, and if usually camel drivers
don't go, people won't be paying attention, and then once in a
month when a camel driver is going there, you won't have noticed
that, you know, that it grew a foot further and it's going
to knock the guy off his camel. But the גמרא Gemara I
guess points out at least in theory though, you can regularly be
checking and fixing, and therefore our משנה mishna could in theory work
even according to the רבנן. rabbanan. Okay, last case, or second last
case. רבי יהודה אומר גמל טעון פשתן וחבילת זמורה. Rabbi Yehuda omer
gamal taun pishtan ve-havilat zemora. You don't go by a person by
the height of the person riding on the camel, but of a
camel laden down with, what do you call it, with flax. So
the גמרא Gemara says, איבעיא להו. Iba'ya le-hu. שיעורא דרבי יהודה נפיש
או דילמא שיעורא דרבנן נפיש. Shiura de-Rabbi Yehuda nafish o dilma shiura
de-rabbanan nafish. Which one is higher? Which one is a greater measure?
The guy sitting on the camel or the flax on the camel?
פשיטא דשיעורא דרבנן נפיש. Pshita de-shiura de-rabbanan nafish. It has to be
that the רבנן's rabbanan is a higher mount. דאי סלקא דעתך שיעורא
דרבי יהודה נפיש רבנן בשיעורא דרבי יהודה היכי עבידי. De-i salka daitach
shiura de-Rabbi Yehuda nafish rabbanan be-shiura de-Rabbi Yehuda heichi avidi. Everybody agrees
sometimes you've got a guy riding on top of a camel and
sometimes you've got a camel with flax on it. So if the
flax height was higher than the person riding, then how could the
רבנן rabbanan be okay with just the height of the person riding?
What about the scenarios where there will be flax on the camel?
Now, of course you could say maybe we're not so concerned about
that, that's just property damage, that's not a person being damaged. But
anyway, all of our cases here were about property damage. So if
the flax height was higher than the person height, there's no way
the רבנן rabbanan would not have had to demand that it had
to have clearance for the flax as well. So now the גמרא
Gemara turns to the obvious opposite question. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ואלא מאי שיעורא דרבנן נפיש רבי יהודה בשיעורא דרבנן מאי עביד. Ve-ela
mai shiura de-rabbanan nafish Rabbi Yehuda be-shiura de-rabbanan mai avid.
So how does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda accommodate the Rabbis' case, right?
So how does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says it's enough to
have at the height of the flocks, what what is he going
to how does he accommodate the scenario where a guy is riding
on top of the camel? So the גמרא Gemara says, no, אפשר
דגחין וחליף efshar de-gachin ve-chalif to say that's not a problem. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda could say you don't need it to be the
height of a guy, because if a guy is riding and he
sees the branch coming up, he'll just duck down. So I don't
need it to be the height of the guy. I do need
it to be the height of the flocks. There's nothing you can
do with the load that's on top of the camel. So at
height of the flocks it has to be. But the height of
the guy it doesn't, the guy could just drop, duck down. You
know, there's like the old joke, right? These two guys are in
a truck that's thirty-two feet off the ground and they pass an
over and they're up to an overpass and it says, clearance twenty-eight
feet. So one of them looks to the other and says, you
see any
cops? So because you can't actually do anything, of course, once it's
too high. And there actually have been cases where the whole tops
of trucks have been ripped off because they did not pay attention
to the clearance. Okay, last two lines of the גמרא. Gemara. ר'
שמעון אומר כל אילן כנגד המשקולת מפני הטומאה. Rabbi Shimon omer kol
ilan k-neged ha-mishkolet mi-p'nei ha-tuma. תנא, Tana, we taught in a ברייתא,
Braitah, מפני אהל הטומאה, mi-p'nei ohel ha-tuma, because of the אהל ohel
there will be a dead body or part of a dead body
and it'll carry it and it'll all be under the same overhang.
פשיטא, Pshita, obviously, says the גמרא, Gemara, מפני הטומאה תנן, mi-p'nei ha-tuma
tnan, it says because of the טומאה. tuma. No, אם מתניתין הוה
אמינא דילמא מייתי עורבא טומאה ושדי התם. im matnitin hava amina dilma
maisei urva tuma ve-shadi hatam. No, because if it was for the
משנה, Mishna, I might have thought it's a problem of an אהל,
ohel, I might have thought it's a problem that a raven would
drop a piece something טמא tamei on one of the branches, and
the problem would be that the טומאה tuma would be coming from
on top of the branch but not being carried by the אהל
ohel from something underneath the branches. What difference does that make? So
the גמרא Gemara says, וסגי בדילולי בעלמא, ve-sagi bi-dilulei be-alma, and then
it would have been enough to prune the branches. As long as
you thinned out the branches enough that nothing no piece of טומאה,
tuma, no dead carcass or whatever could be sustained by it, you
would say that's okay if you're only concerned with something being dropped
on the branches. קמשמע לן, ka-mashma lan, that the concern is not
something dropped on the branches but the אהל ohel created by the
branches, so pruning is not enough and you have to totally cut
it all away so that there is no overhang. With that we
finish the second פרק. perek. הדרן עלך לא יחפור. Hadran alach lo
yachfor.